Hey guys, Shandai welcome back and in
part two we are going to start with
consumer and consumer group and if you
have not seen the part one in the part
one we have already covered
producer
topic
partition and about segment and index
and broker.
Okay now let's uncover another important
part consumer and consumer groups. So
there are two different things. So
producer already done. Kafka broker
which is also known as server also done
topic we also know about it and
partitions. So now here if you see we
have consumer group and consumers within
the group.
So we can have multiple
groups. So let's say I have created one
group notification. Another group I have
created analytics
and you can join any one of the group
which you want. Okay. So let's say I
have joined consumer group uh
notification group. I can also join
analytics group. Okay. So that is
possible but you have to be part of one
of the group and it has one rule. One
important rule is that
consumer in one group different
consumers in one group can only read
different partition.
Okay. So multiple consumer in a same
group cannot read same partition.
Okay. And the rule number two is that
different consumer in different group
can read same partition. So now here in
this case let's say that so this
consumer is part of notification group
so it is reading this partition one
similarly this consumer is part of
analytics group it can also read the
same partition that is possible but this
is not possible that in the notification
these two consumer is reading the same
partition that is not possible
okay
and like you have very multiple
scenarios like very simple is like you
have three partitions Three consumers
all reading different partitions one to
one consumers are less than partitions.
So consumers can take care of more than
one partition. Okay. But here if you see
that no two consumer in a same group
notification let's say the all part of
notification group. No two consumer of
same group reading the same partition.
for they are taking care of different
different partitions but they can take
multiple partitions.
If consumers are greater than partition
it is possible that some consumer might
be idle. Okay
this two I have already told you
multiple consumers
can read
same partition if there are part of
different groups.
Okay.
Now this is important that each consumer
group maintain partition wise offset
independently.
What does that mean? So here if you see
that in a consumer group let's say
notification
you have consumer one, consumer two,
consumer three. Now let's say consumer
is reading
partition zero of topic order. Let's say
consumer three is reading let's say
partition one of order topic.
So after reading let's say it has read
till offset 500. It has read till offset
300.
Now it need to store this information.
So that's what I mentioned each consumer
group maintains partition wise offset
independently. So now let's say that
this group notification
for this topic this partition
this many offsets are processed
successfully.
this group let's say notification within
a notification
this topic for this topic this partition
let's say partition one this many events
are processed successfully
so here if you have noticed that we are
maintaining group wise information
not consumer let's say consumer one
of group notification
this topic order topic
this partition
has retail offset let's say 500.
So we are not storing consumer wise we
are storing group wise itself. Why?
Because let's say in future
this consumer went down. Okay. And if
new consumer comes up let's say this
consumer need to consumer two now need
to take over. What it can do is it can
simply ask hey
I am belongs to this notification group
tell me that this event this topic order
and this partition
till how many events are processed. So
it can simply find out from this
information that okay for this group
notification this topic this partition
till 500 it is process you can start
from 501
okay
so this information is maintained.
Now another important question is that
where does this information is stored.
So very very important and basic part I
would say that always have that Kafka
major strength is is partition
topic
plus partition. Okay and partition is
something where actually data is stored.
So if anything has to be stored in Kafka
it make use of topic and partition its
core strength. So this information is
also stored in topic
partition
only. Okay, no difference.
So which topic
there is a topic internally Kafka will
create for us is consumer offset. So see
this that this is the Kafka UI.
uh when I started the server in my
system I uh opened the UI after starting
the server and here if you see I haven't
created any topic yet but if you see in
internally it is created not created by
me so it created this offset_consumer
offset and how many partition by default
it created 50 for us
okay so all this information is stored
in this topic
Okay, no matter how many consumer groups
you have, okay, all everybody stores
maintain this information offset related
information
they are stored here in this consumer
offset like which topic which partition
till what point has been processed
successfully.
Okay. So now understand with this
example
I have a producer I have only for this
example let's say I have only one broker
Kafka broker one okay and this Kafka
broker I have one event uh one topic
order events and I have created three
partitions partition zero partition one
partition two and this is the internal
topic which has been created uh by Kafka
okay this one_consumer
offset and 50 partition it has created.
Okay. Now let's say consumer one is
taking care
to read this order events topic and
partition zero and let's say it has read
till 500
offset.
Now it want to store this information.
What information it need to store? Hey
this group notification
this offset order events
this topic partition zero till 500 are
processed events are processed
successfully it need to store this
capture this snapshot let's say okay so
now what it will do is it has to where
where this information will store it
will store in this topic_consumer
offset
Okay. So this is the message it will
publish to the broker.
Okay. Hey
this topic I want to store
this information
notification group ID notification
information
topic
partition and the committed offset till
where I have process. it will store this
information.
Okay. So here if you see that
I am doing computing the partition like
in which partition because see you have
50 partition out of this 50 partition
one partition would take care of this
group.
Okay. So which group
we can compute it also like which group
is ultimately going to or which uh this
group
data ultimately going to which
partition. So generally logic is that
hash of notification group ID this group
ID whatever the group you have that ID
mod number of partition you have in this
topic consumer offset. So we have 50. So
now let's say you got 23. So means
partition 23 will hold
all the offset related information for
this group.
Okay.
So you might be thinking that hey why
you need to compute this partition uh
information because if you can recall
from the broker
okay I told you that broker do not store
all topic
and all of its
partition.
No broker store only some topic
and some of its
partition
okay only some topic some of its
partition so in when we have multiple
brokers let's say broker one broker two
I I don't want to have multiple broker
scenarios now but I think it's critical
to clear this part why we are computing
this partition where which partition
this message should go. So now let's say
we have broker one, broker two, broker
three. I told you that each broker
stores some topic some partition. Now
let's say broker two is the one which
stores
consumer offset and let's say it hold
partition one to partition 20. Broker 3
is one which have consumer
offset which hold let's say partition 21
to partition 50 like this. Let's say
this is distributed across multiple
brokers.
So when you know that okay partition 23
is the one where my information should
go
should go why I'm saying that because of
this formula you compute the hash of
group ID mod 50. So you will always get
get same partition. So whenever you have
to store your offset details, it always
goes to same partition. So now you need
to know that hey who holds this topic
and this partition because in case of
multiple brokers.
Okay. So this partition 23 who hosted.
So here in this case that I'll tell you
I'll come to that like how it determine
that B3 is the one that host partition
23 because B3 has from partition 21 to
partition 50. So it need to connect to
broker 3.
Don't worry about this. We'll come to
that later when we will discuss about
cluster. But here I just wanted to tell
you that why it determine this partition
because it need to determine which
broker it need to connect to which
broker host this partition. Okay. So
once it determine that okay this is the
broker which host this partition this
topic partition it will connect to that
broker. This broker is nothing but a
server. So it will connect to that
server and say that hey store this
information in your logs.
Okay.
So why this information is stored? I
told you that when this consumer got
crash and say new consumer comes up they
can make use of this consumer offset to
determine from where they have to start
again. So what they will do is first
let's say notification group. Okay. So
what it will do is let's say server uh
consumer one got crashed and consumer
two comes up and it has been assigned
that hey you have the responsibility of
partition zero which earlier consumer
one was taken care of. Now how consumer
2 will know from where I need to start.
What it will do is it will first find
out the partition that hey hash of group
ID mod 50 this partition. Now it will
find out that hey who holds this
partition this topic this partition who
which broker host it. So let's say it
find out that okay broker three. So this
consumer connects with broker 3 and say
that hey give me for this topic let's
say this topic this partition till where
the data has been processed. Let's say
partition zero in this example partition
zero. Tell me for this topic let's say
order even topic partition zero till
where it has been processed.
Now this broker can check its log for
this topic for this topic.
Okay, it can check the logs for this
partition
and return the information.
At this point of time you might have
confusion about this multiple brokers
and all that's totally fine because
those things will get clear when we jump
to cluster but at this point all I want
you to have understand is that what is
consumer group what is consumer
okay and they store offset related
information that's all I wanted that you
clear this part so they store the offset
that okay
this group this topic this partition
till this it is processed. So it is
stored in one of the topic. Okay. And
whenever any server consumer got crashed
they can fetch the details from the
topic. Okay.
And uh whatever the different brokers
and all those things that things will
get clear.
Okay.
Now we have is like offset commit
strategies. One thing might be coming
that okay what are the different
strategy let's say I have told that
consumer one has read partition zero of
let's say topic
uh order events after 500 it decided
that okay I need to commit but what is
the strategy why after 500 or what are
the different strategies so one is auto
commit. So you can uh tell the time auto
doit interval dot milliseconds that
after every 5 seconds you have to
commit. Okay. So let's say time zero
consumer polls [snorts]
get even from 0 to 99.
At time one consumer processing the
events. Okay. And after 5 seconds it
will autocommit the trigger. But there
is a problem that what if consumer
crashes
at 50.
Since autocommit has already happened
means a detail has been gone into this
consumer
offsets
topic
that hey this group notification group
for this topic let's say order event
topic this partition partition zero 99
till it is processed now
because it is auto commit happen right
so it is already added into this
consumer offset topic. Now if consumer
crash at 50th and it will restart and it
will fetch from this topic. Hey till
where I have done it will give that hey
99 you have done you have to start from
100.
So you have lost certain information. So
this is risky. Auto commit is always
risky. So best strategy is that manual
command you decide when you want. So one
way is that in a batch let's say you
done the polling you got 100 events at a
time okay you process all event and uh
once you completed then
you push okay once all done then you
push and then continue with the next
batch. So what happen is that even if
you crash okay let's say you crashed at
70 so you will still previous
information is let's say zero
and you got like 0 to 99 badge but after
with while you are processing the 70 you
got crash and when you restart and you
again fetch hey what was the last I have
processed you can say that zero you have
to start again
so it's only possible that you might
have to uh duplicate processing.
Okay. So in the manual commit apart from
batch there is also is that every
instead of let's say you complete the
full batch after that you do a commit
after every event process you try to do
commit but
that is not recommended because
generally Kafka is used when there are
lot of events. Okay. So with every
events it's not recommended that you
have to make a call to the server.
Okay. So appropriate batch size we have
to find out like uh based upon our
business and this is the recommended
approach.
Okay. So we know about little bit about
consumer
and consumer group.
Don't worry the part where we have
discussed about multiple broker because
now we are slowly going into the
advanced level of the cluster. That's
where the multiple broker comes into the
picture.
At this point of time my expectation is
that I am able to
actually the definition should be clear
for producer topic partition broker
consumer and consumer group.
Now you can say that the real Kafka
comes into the picture the advance.
Okay. What is Kafka cluster? Kafka
cluster is nothing but a group of
brokers working together to provide
scalability, fall tolerant and high
availability.
Very very important. Scalability means
distribute load across multiple servers.
Fall tolerance means continue operate
even if broker fails. High availability
means no single point of failure. Kafka
do not have a single point of failure.
So in this example now see KL clavka
cluster is has it has multiple broker.
So one broker what does one broker has
is one broker can have
some topics and of some topic it can
have some of their partition.
Okay and Kafka custer we have multiple
such brokers.
We have multiple search brokers which
has c some topics and of those topics
some partitions. [snorts]
Now everything need to be coordinated.
Okay.
It takes care of certain requests. It
take care of certain requests. It takes
care of certain request. That's why
scalability distributed load across
multiple server. These are all servers.
Fault tolerance. Even if one broker
fails, even if one partition fails, even
if one topic fails,
the Kafka is up and running.
No single point of failure at any point
of time. Whether broker fails, whether
partition fails, whether topic fails,
it's up and running. How? I will show
you.
Okay. Now the question is how?
How this multi-broker architecture where
we have multiple broker able to achieve
this three things
very important part the leader follower
partition
okay
for each partition
for each partition I'm talking about one
broker is leader and others are
followers
example understand this with all
everything with an example let's say You
have created a topic order events
and you have a partition three partition
zero partition one partition two. Now
there is something you also tell the
replication factor how many replicas you
want.
Okay. So
three partition of topics order events
will be created like we have tell order
events I want three topics uh three
partition partition zero partition one
partition two. Now for each partition I
have said two replica means there should
be two copy.
So partition zero has two replica is
like one leader and one follower.
Partition one, two replica. One leader,
one follower.
Okay. Partition two, one leader, one
follower. Two replica.
And all these, so total how many
partitions? Six partitions.
Okay. Out of the six,
three are leader,
three are follower.
Okay. So all these six partitions are
distributed among the brokers.
So now here if you see in the Kafka
cluster we have three brokers. Broker
one, broker two, broker three. Now let's
say that broker one has this topic order
events. It has this topic order events
and it host
only partition zero.
Okay. So
this topic this broker this topic it
host one leader only partition zero is
the leader here.
Okay and partition zero leader here. So
it has one follower right. So one
follower would be into different broker.
Okay. So partition zero for this event
for this topic. So order events topic
partition zero follower is present into
broker three. Okay. And its leader is
present into
broker one.
Similarly partition one of topic order
events.
So partition one. Huh. So here if you
see partition one leader is
present into broker two. Broker two has
this topic order event. It hosts the
leader partition one.
Okay. And it has a follower, right? One
follower. So it would be into different
broker. So let's say broker one has this
follower. Similarly, partition two, one
leader, one follower. So partition two
leader is present into this broker three
and it is follower into different broker
it is present here.
So now here if you see that
no broker holds all the information.
So broker one has partition zero leader
information and this is just a follower
backup of the partition one.
Okay. And but partition one leader is
present into broker two.
So this leader is the one which actually
responsible for read and write into a
particular partition. For example, you
are interested into order events and you
want to write into partition zero. This
producer want to write into partition
zero.
Now who will write it? Partition zero
follower is there. Partition zero leader
is there. Always leader is the one which
is responsible for read and write. Only
when leader fails then only followers
comes into the picture. They become a
leader. But till then you can say that
followers are nothing but a standby
which only task is to stay up to date
with the leader. That's all.
Okay. So now if you remember from the
producer okay so what uh it has a topic
when it publish an event it has a topic
let's say order
events
and let's say key
let's say order id and then your uh
record some JSON record and if you
remember we were doing hash of this
order ID
and how many partition are there in this
topic order event let's say currently
three and it got let's say partition one
so now this producer need to know that
which broker host this partition one for
this topic so order events okay
partition one leader it need to find out
the leader which broker host the leader
of partition one okay because then it
has to pass the request to that broker
only okay the same thing I told you in
previous video about consumer consumer
need to publish an event to consumer
offsets topic okay and that consumer
offset topic has 50 partition so that's
why they were doing hash of group ID
mod 50 and if they find out that okay
partition 23 which broker host the
partition 23 leader because leader can
only take care of right
And that's where they have to connect to
that particular server.
So what is the leader responsibility?
Leader responsibility handle all
producer rights, handle all consumer
reads, maintain the partition logs.
Okay. And coordinate with follower.
Follower responsibilities. Replicate
data from leader. Stay in sync with
leader. Ready to become a leader. If
current leader fails, do not serve
client. Followers never serve clients.
Only leader does.
Okay.
[snorts]
So this is clear. Now one question might
have comes to your mind.
Who decide which broker host which
partition replica?
Which partition replica become leader?
Which partition replica stay have
follower? So we have done this right.
Okay. Broker one contains partition zero
as leader and partition one follower.
Broker two has partition one as leader,
partition two follower. It is stored
this. But who decides that?
Okay. Because see they are different
servers.
But who decides
which broker host which topic and out of
this topic which partition it will host
as a leader and which partition it will
host as a follower who decide this.
That's where our controller comes into
the picture. So which I will cover in
the next part. Okay. I don't want to go
fast but if you have any doubt till here
let me know in the comment section we
can discuss further but at this point of
time the leader follower partition
should be clear
okay see you in the next